Guide to the Jenkins Arcade and Empire Building, Pittsburgh, Pa. and the Empire Hotel, New York, N.Y., Collection of Plans and Drawings, 1897-1953 AIS.1984.01
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Jenkins Arcade and Empire Building, Pittsburgh, Pa. and the Empire Hotel, New York, N.Y., Collection of Plans and Drawings
1897-1953
ULS Archives & Special Collections
AIS.1984.01
573.75 Linear Feet (oversized drawings and blueprints)
The Jenkins Arcade and Empire Building were long-time Pittsburgh landmarks until they were razed in 1984. The Jenkins Arcade was designed by O. M. Topp in 1910 as an improvment to the original Jenkins Building. The Empire Building, designed by Frederic I. Merrick in 1898, was erected in 1900 on the same block as the Jenkins Building. The collection contains architectural drawings and engineering plans.
History
The Jenkins Arcade and Empire Building were long-time Pittsburgh landmarks which occupied the block bordered by Penn Avenue, Fifth Street, Stanwick (formally Ferry) Street, and Liberty Avenue until they were razed in 1984. Designed by O. M. Topp in 1910, the Jenkins Arcade was built as an improvement upon a grocery warehouse constructed for Tomas C. Jenkins in 1864 at the corner of Penn Avenue and Fifth Street. The Empire Building, designed by Frederic I. Merrick in 1898, was erected in 1900 on the remaining half of the block where the Jenkins Building was located, along what was then known as Ferry Street, between Penn Avenue and Liberty Avenue. Frederic I. Merrick also designed the Empire Hotel at 63rd and Broadway in New York City during 1922 and 1923.
The original Jenkins Building was also designed by O. M. Topp and was a victim of the Great Fire of 1897. At this time, the Jenkins brothers chose to reconstruct the building and eventually turn it into a shopping arcade and office building. In its day, it was considered the largest and finest arcade in the United States. The building was seven-stories tall and constructed of steel with terra-cotta tiling through out. The imposing exterior was handsomely finished in vitrified brick and terra-cotta trimings. The Jenkins Arcade was officially designated an historic landmark in 1972. Until 1984, when the building was razed for the construction of the Fifth Avenue Place office building, few changes had been made to it.
Scope and Content Notes
The architectural drawings and engineering plans included in this collection are incomplete. They were discovered by workmen in the course of the razing of the buildings. The collection consists of 459 items including india ink drawings on vellum, blueprints, as well as pencil and ink drawings on paper. The materials in the collection have been dated between 1897 and 1953. The drawings and plans are arranged in three series relating to the content of the materials. Within each series the materials are arranged according to size, medium, architectural subject, and building. The collection is all oversized materials housed in map cases.
The collection contains a set of architectural drawings of the Jenkins Arcade and the companion buildings, the Jenkins and Empire Buildings. The largest group of material consists of mechanical engineering plans and blueprints by architects, O. M. Topp and Edward B. Lee. The engineering plans mostly include structural steel shop drawings of reconstruction after the fire of 1897 and the construction of the Arcade in 1910. A few of the drawings contain exterior and interior details. Construction cost estimates and a list of the building contractors are also written on the drawings.
A small collection of blueprints by Frederic I. Merrick show the plans for the alterations and additions to the Empire Building. There is also a set of drawings on linen and other interior details of the Empire Hotel, New York, NY done by Frederic I. Merrick in 1922 and 1923.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of William J. Swazuk, January 12, 1984.
Previous Citation
Jenkins Arcade and Empire Building, Pittsburgh, Pa. and the Empire Hotel, New York, N.Y., Collection of Plans and Drawings 1897-1953, ais198401, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Pittsburgh (Pa.) -- Buildings, structures, etc.; Drawings (Visual works); Blueprints (Reprographic copies); Architecture; Architecture -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Empire Building (Pittsburgh, Pa.); Empire Hotel (New York, N.Y.); Jenkins Arcade (Pittsburgh, Pa.); Lee, Edward B. (Edward Brown); Merrick, Frederic I.; Topp, O. M.
- Engineering Drawings, 1897-1910; I.
  - American Bridge Company, Ambridge, PA-Jenkins Arcade Building, 121 drawings (india ink on vellum), size: 62.5 cm x 32 cm, June 9 - August 25, 1910 (Map-case 4, Drawer 3, Folder Series 1)
  - Carnegie Steel Co.-Jenkins Building, 31 drawings (india ink on vellum) (Map-case 4, Drawer 3, Folder Series 2)
  - Carnegie Steel Co. of Jenkins Building, 33 drawings (india ink on vellum), size: 76 cm x 46 cm, August 19 - September 17, 1897 (Map-case 4, Drawer 3, Folder Series 3)
  - Carnegie Steel Co., Elevator and trestle work- Jenkins Building, 25 drawings (india ink on vellum), size: 45.5 cm x 31 cm, October 5 - October 16, 1897 (Map-case 4, Drawer 3, Folder Series 4)
  - Carnegie Steel Co., Erection of Jenkins Building, 133 drawings (india ink on vellum), size: 45.5 cm x 31 cm, August 5 - October, 1897 (Map-case 4, Drawer 3, Folder Series 5)
  - Carnegie Steel Co., Tank Supports- Jenkins Building, 5 drawings (india ink on vellum), size: 46 cm x 30.5 cm, December 20, 1897 (Map-case 4, Drawer 3, Folder Series 6)
  - American Bridge Co., Ambridge, PA- Structural Steel for Jenkins Building, 48 drawings (india ink on paper), size: 43.5 cm x 28.5 cm, March 1 - May 5, 1909 (Map-case 4, Drawer 3, Folder Series 7)
- Accounting Records, 1910-1911; II.
  - Ledger Sheet, Thompson-Starrett Co., 1 sheet, size: 65 cm x 13 cm, December 15, 1910 (Map-case 4, Drawer 4, Folder Series 8)
  - Cost estimates, Jenkins Arcade alterations, Thompson-Starrett Co., 8 sheets, size: 33 cm x 23 cm, 1911 (Map-case 4, Drawer 4, Folder Series 9)
  - Audit, Jenkins Arcade alterations, Thompson-Starrett Co., 11 sheets (bound), size: 33 cm x 23 cm, May 22, 1911 (Map-case 4, Drawer 4, Folder Series 10)
- Architectural Plans, Elevations, Details, Alterations, Miscellaneous, 1910-1953; III.
  Scope and Content Notes
  Series III includes individual, oversized drawings and blueprints that range from to 42 x 42 centimeters to 3 x 5 meters. All information about the drawings such as date, medium, content, building, and architect will be noted when it is known.
  - "Building for the Thos. C. Jenkins Est.", Elevations and interior details, (photostat), 1. (Map-case 4, Drawer 4)
  - Elevations, Jenkins Arcade, [O. M. Topp, architect], (Blueprint), May 17, 1910; revised June 1, 1910; 2.
  - Corner bays, adjoining brick mullion, Jenkins Arcade, [O. M. Topp, architect], (drawing on tissue), June 14, 1910; 3.
  - Elevation, Possibly Jenkins Arcade, (drawing on paper), 4.
  - Various Plans of Jenkins Arcade Building, [O. M. Topp, architect], (set of 12 sheets), 5.
  - Various elevations, profiles of Jenkins Arcade Building, (6 sheets), 6.
  - Flood gate detail, [Edward B. Lee, architect], (Blueprint), 7.
  - First floor plan, [Edward B. Lee, architect], (Blueprint), 8.
  - Second floor plan, [Edward B. Lee, architect], (Blueprint), 9.
  - Third floor plan, [Edward B. Lee, architect], (Blueprint), 10.
  - Third floor electric plan, [O. M. Topp, architect], (India ink on vellum), August 6, 1910; 11.
  - Fourth floor plan [revised], [Edward B. Lee, architect], (Blueprint), May 26, 1909; 12.
  - Roof plan, [Edward B. Lee, architect], (Blueprint), 13. (Map-case 4, Drawer 5)
  - Roof heating plan, [Edward B. Lee, architect], (Blueprint), June 22, 1910; 14.
  - Proposed sign for Jenkins Arcade, [G. C. O'Brien, Builder], (Blueprint), 1910; 15.
  - Proposed alterations and additions (scheme 2), main floor, [Edward B. Lee, architect], (Blueprint), 16.
  - Proposed alterations and additions (schemes 1 2), balcony, [Edward B. Lee, architect], (Blueprint), 17.
  - Elevation details, [Edward B. Lee, architect], (Blueprint), 18.
  - Fifth St. elevation, [Edward B. Lee, architect], (Blueprint), 19.
  - Elevation details, doors, etc., [Edward B. Lee, architect], (Blueprint), 20. (Map-case 4, Drawer 6)
  - Plumbing layout, addition, all floors, [Edward B. Lee, architect], (Blueprint), 21.
  - Elevation, third floor, cornice, [Edward B. Lee, architect], (Drawing on tissue), 22.
  - Cornice detail, third floor, [Edward B. Lee, architect], (Drawing on tissue), 23.
  - Pilaster, [Edward B. Lee, architect], (drawing on tissue), 24.
  - Shandrels, second floor, [Edward B. Lee, architect], (drawing on tissue), 25.
  - Elevations, perimeter of Jenkins Estate, [Cooper Co.], (Drawing), December, 1913; 26.
  - Mezzanine floor plan, (blueprint), 27.
  - Flood barricade, details, [W. S. Tyler Co.], December 19, 1936; 28.
  - Dr. Vankirk, et al., [Caulk Equipment Co.], October 10, 1937; 29.
  - Flood gates, (Drawing), February 10, 1945; 30.
  - Storefront for J. Fedele, [Altehof Brown, architects], (Blueprint), July 24, 1946; 31.
  - Doig Optical alterations, [George R. Simmons, architect], (Blueprint), May 6, 1947; 32.
  - Dr. Bartram's office, rms. 5035-38, [A. L. Morrison, architect], (Blueprint), August 28, 1951; 33.
  - Dentist's office (Dr. Brown), [Caulk Equipment Co.], (Blueprint), October 26, 1953; 34.
  - Alterations to Empire Building, [Alfred M. Murks, architect], (Blueprints, sets of 10 sheets), 35. (Map-case 4, Drawer 7)
  - Elevations (alterations and additons), Empire Building, [Frederic I. Merrick, architect], (10 Blueprints [bound]), 36.
  - Elevation, Empire Hotel, [Frederic I. Merrick, architect], (India ink on vellum), February 5, 1923; 37.
  - Lounge, lobby details, Empire Hotel, [Frederic I. Merrick, architect], (India ink on vellum), January 1, 1923; 38.
  - Elevations, dining room, Empire Hotel, [Frederic I. Merrick, architect], (India ink on vellum), January 31, 1923; 39.
  - Details, lounge, Empire Hotel, [Frederic I. Merrick, architect], (India ink on vellum), October 17, 1922; 40. (Map-case 4, Drawer 8)
  - Facade elevation, between columns 65 & 66, Empire Hotel, [Frederic I. Merrick, architect], (India ink on vellum), September 8, 1922; 41.
  - Transverse section, Empire Hotel, [Frederic I. Merrick, architect], (India ink on vellum), August 14, 1922; 42.
  - Elevations, Empire Hotel, [Frederic I. Merrick, architect], (India ink on vellum), August 4, 1922; 43.